

Andrea Dal Pozzolo, PhD

Born in Schio (Italy) on August 19, 1987 Address: Oberdorfstrasse 13, 8107 Buchs-Zurich, Switzerland +41795799135 • dalpozz@gmail.com • www.linkedin.com/in/dalpozz

SUMMARY

I'm passionate about data and I define myself a Data Scientist: I'm an expert in Machine Learning, Data Mining and statistical techniques. In my daily job I use statistical models to extract knowledge from data and provide insights.

EDUCATION

Université Libre de Bruxelles, Brussels, Belgium

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.) in Computer Science

Jan 2012 - Dec 2015

- Thesis: Adaptive Machine Learning for Credit Card Fraud Detection
- · Adviser: Prof. Gianluca Bontempi
- Research areas: Machine Learning, Data Mining, Statistics and Fraud Detection.

Università di Bologna, Bologna, Italy

Master of Science (M.S.) in Applied Statistics and Actuarial Science

• Thesis: Comparison of Data Mining Techniques for Insurance Claim Prediction

• Final grade: 110/110 Summa Cum Laude

Bachelor of Science (B.S.) in Statistics for Finance and Insurance

Sep 2009 – Dec 2011

Sep 2009 – Dec 2011

• Second year at University of Glasgow (UK), Erasmus student

• Final grade: 110/110 Summa Cum Laude

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Politecnico di Milano, Milan, Italy

Visiting researcher at Dipartimento Elettronica e Informazione (DEI)

Apr 2015 – Jun 2015

· Supervisors: Prof. Giacomo Boracchi

• Research areas: Credit Card Fraud Detection, Concept Drift, Active Learning.

University of Notre Dame, Notre Dame, Indiana, USA

Visiting researcher at Data Inference Analytics and Learning Lab (DIAL). May 2014 – Jun 2014

• Supervisors: Prof. Nitesh V Chawla

• Research areas: Unbalanced Classification, Concept Drift, Data Streams.

ACADEMIC AWARDS

BruFence project (total 1M 192K €), Innoviris (Brussels Region).	2015 - 2018
Doctiris PhD scholarship (320K €), Innoviris (Brussels Region).	2012 - 2015
Travel Grant for 2015 IJCNN conference (800 \$), IEEE	Jul 2015
Travel Grant for research collaborations (1500 €), Université Libre de Bruxelles	Apr 2015
Master Thesis scholarship (2000 €), Università di Bologna	Sep 2011
Erasmus mundus exchange scholarship (3000 €) ,Università di Bologna	Sep 2007

WORK EXPERIENCE

Ernst & Young, Zurich, Switzerland

Consultant | Quant & Analytics team

Since Apr 2016

- Application of Machine Learning algorithms for conduct risk and anomaly detection.
- Anti money laundering model audit using Machine Learning techniques.
- · Credit and Market risk models audit for major Swiss Banks.

VASCO Data Security, Wemmel, Belgium

Decision Analytics Consultant

Jan 2016 – Mar 2016

- Implementation of Fraud Detection Systems based on Machine Learning algorithms.
- Definition of factors used by business rules for fraud prevention.
- Development of a Link Analysis application supporting fraud investigations.

Machine Learning Group - ULB, Brussels, Belgium

Researcher

Jan 2012 – Dec 2015

- $\bullet \ \ Development \ of \ Machine \ Learning \ algorithms \ for \ Fraud \ Detection \ in \ credit \ cards.$
- Collaboration with the fraud detection team of Worldline S.A (Brussels, Belgium).
- Supervision and coaching of master students.

Directa Sim, Turin, Italy

Analyst Aug 2009 – Jul 2011

- Supervision of VisualTrader development (online stock trading platform).
- Development of trading systems and market scanners.
- Customer support for the trading platform.

Allianz, Milan, Italy

Life actuary assistant

Nov 2008 - Feb 2009

- Balance analysis and report according to US GAAP and IFRS regulation (HB2).
- Gained a basic working knowledge of Moses and Prohet software.
- Worked in a team of 5 people having balance deadline to respect.

Absolute Quality, Glasgow, Scotland

Computer Game tester/translator

Oct 2007 - Nov 2007

- Translation in Italian and consistency with English.
- Develop analytical ability making sure that transcript mach my report.

Riccardo's restaurant, London, England

Waiter Jun 2005 – Sep 2005

- · Self-funded study and work experience in London for three months.
- Demonstrated my ability to adapt and thrive in new and different environments.

IT SKILLS R, Python, H20, SQL, SAS, HTML, Java, C++, SPSS, LATEX, Microsoft Office suite (ECDL licence).

SOFTWARE Developed an R package called *unbalanced* for classification with unbalanced distributions.

PUBLICATIONS<u>A. Dal Pozzolo</u>, O. Caelen, and G. Bontempi, "When is undersampling effective in unbalanced classification tasks?," in *Machine Learning and Knowledge Discovery in Databases*

(ECML-PKDD), Porto, Portugal, 2015.

<u>A. Dal Pozzolo</u>, O. Caelen, R. A Johnson and G. Bontempi, "Calibrating Probability with Undersampling for Unbalanced Classification," in *Proceedings of 2015 IEEE Symposium Series on Computational Intelligence (SSCI)*, Cape Town, South Africa, 2015.

<u>A. Dal Pozzolo</u>, G. Boracchi, O. Caelen, C. Alippi and G. Bontempi, "Credit Card Fraud Detection and Concept-Drift Adaptation with Delayed Supervised Information," in *Proceedings of 2015 International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN)*, Killarney, Ireland, 2015.

<u>A. Dal Pozzolo</u>, O. Caelen, Y. Le Borgne, S. Waterschoot, and G. Bontempi, "Learned lessons in credit card fraud detection from a practitioner perspective," *Expert Systems with Applications*, vol. 41, no. 10, pp. 4915–4928, 2014.

<u>A. Dal Pozzolo</u>, R. A Johnson, O. Caelen, S. Waterschoot, N. V Chawla, and G. Bontempi, "Using HDDT to avoid instances propagation in unbalanced and evolving data streams," in *Proceedings of 2014 International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN)*, Beijing, China, 2014.

<u>A. Dal Pozzolo</u>, O. Caelen, S. Waterschoot, and G. Bontempi, "Racing for unbalanced methods selection," in *Proceedings of the 14th International Conference on Intelligent Data Engineering and Automated Learning (IDEAL)*, Hefei, China, 2013.

LANGUAGES Italian: Native language.

English: Fluent (speaking, reading, writing).

French: Fluent (speaking, reading). Intermediate (writing).

German: Beginner (speaking, reading).

INTERESTS Cycling, Basketball, Economics, Digital photography.

REFERENCES Available upon request.

[Last update on 2016-12-18]